Guide to the W. J. Linton Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Graphic Material, 1838–1913; Series IV; 7.22; 6 boxes
  - Prints
    Contains wood engravings by Linton in albums, in groups of loose prints, and as individual prints.
    - "Engravings in Wood by W. J. Linton and Assistants", 1842–1849 (Box 18, Folder 362)
      Album likely compiled by Linton and afterward owned by William Fowler Hopson.
    - Album of engravings, undated (Box 19, Folder 363)
      Inscribed by Linton: "My own early work"; album was inherited by Ellen Wade Linton.
    - Unbound album of engravings collected by Lancelot Linton, undated (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 364)
      Work completed in England before 1863.
    - "Wood-Engraving", 1851–1875 (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 365)
      Album likely compiled by Linton; divided into two marked sections: "Work in England" and "Work in America."
    - Bookplate for James Terry, undated (Box 10, Folder 295)
      Signed proof sheet and plates.
    - Engravings, 1868–1913 (Box 10, Folder 296)
      Clipped from publications, proofs, tear sheets, and journal covers.
    - Engravings (Box 17, Folder 357)
    - "Edwin Booth as Benedick," after William J. Hennessey, 1870 (Box 17, Folder 358)
      For Edwin Booth in Twelve Dramatic Characters, by William Winter (Boston: J. R. Osgood & Company, 1872).
    - "Weathercote Cave," after Joseph Mallord William Turner, 1887 (Box 17, Folder 359)
      After the painting in the British Museum; accompanied by "Weathercote Cave" engraving by Samuel Middiman (ca. 1750-1831) removed from Thomas Dunham Whitaker's History of Richmondshire (London, 1823).
  - Serials
    - Pen and Pencil, Advertising Supplement (London, 1855), 1855 February 17 (Box 17, Folder 360)
    - American Enterprise (New York, 1871-1872) (Box 17, Folder 361)
      One partial issue (pages 1-2, 9-10) of no. 1, and two full issues and one cover of No. 2.
  - Sketchbooks
    - Sketchbook, 1848–1849 (Box 11, Folder 297)
      Autograph journal of travels in the Lake District illustrated with sketches in graphite and watercolor.
    - Lake sketches, 1862–1863 (Box 11, Folder 298)
      Autograph journal of travels in the Lake District of Westmorland, May 18, 1862 to 1863. Descriptions in verse or prose, illustrated with sketches in graphite and watercolor.
    - Sketchbook, 1863 (Box 11, Folder 299)
      Sketches and drawings in graphite and watercolor made in the Lake District between May and July 1863.
    - Sketchbook, 1863–1864 (Box 11, Folder 300)
      Sketches and drawings in graphite and watercolor made in the Lake District between July and August 1863, and December 1864.
- Personal Papers, 1838–1902; Series V; 0.42; 1 box
  The series holds a small group of Linton's personal papers, including autobiographical entries from contemporary publications, a passport and calling card, his membership certificate from the National Academy of Design, and photographs of his home and grave in Hamden, Connecticut. Important in the series are the earliest minutes of the Walthamstow Working Men's Association in suburban London, for which Linton was secretary.
  - Artist's Annuity Fund membership certificate, 1838 March 22 (Box 12, Folder 301)
  - Calling card, undated (Box 12, Folder 302)
    Engraved card for "W. J. Linton. Portrait Painter, 13 Upper Berkeley Street West."
  - Ephemera related to Joseph Mazzini, 1849–1870 (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 366)
    Newspaper clippings with writings in English, French, and Italian by and about Mazzini, accompanied by a manuscript note in French.
  - Ephemera, other (Box 12, Folder 303)
  - French passport, 1848 February 21 (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 367)
  - Memorandum of Agreement with Charles Scribner's Sons, 1882 November 10 (Box 12, Folder 304)
    An agreement between Linton and Richard Henry Stoddard and the Scribner's firm, for preparing and publishing a collection of English verse. Hectograph copy with autograph signatures.
  - Men of the Time autobiographical entry with autograph corrections, 1866 (Box 12, Folder 305)
    Likely originally written by Linton.
  - National Academy of Design membership certificate, 1883 May 8 (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 368)
    Certificate signed by T. Addison Richards and Daniel Huntington; accompanied by newspaper clipping reporting his election to membership.
  - National Cyclopedia of American Biography autobiographical essay, 1894 June 4 (Box 12, Folder 306)
    Typescript with autograph corrections.
  - Photographs of Appledore and Linton's grave in Hamden, and home in Bearsted, England, undated (Box 12, Folder 307)
  - Poem by Welbore St. Clair Baddeley, undated (Box 12, Folder 308)
    Copied by Linton.
  - Portraits, 1890, undated (Box 12, Folder 309)
  - "Programme of the Birthday Sports", 1874 January 22 (Box 12, Folder 310)
    Autograph program for Margaret Linton's birthday celebration.
  - "Protest against Death-punishment", [1839] (Box 12, Folder 311)
    Written on behalf of "John Frost, Zephaniah Williams, and William Jones, now lying under sentence of death in Her Majesty's gaol at Monmouth" and signed by George Birkbeck, Leigh Hunt, and W. J. Fox. Described in Linton's Threescore and Ten Years (New York: C. Scribner's, 1894).
  - Provisional Rules of the People's Charter Union, 1848 March 17 (Box 12, Folder 312)
    Established at the Finsbury Literary Institution Friday, March 14, 1848.
  - Universal Republic, undated (Box 12, Folder 313)
    Blank enrollment list for an association.
  - Walthamstow Working Men's Association, Minutes, 1839 April (Box 12, Folder 314)
    Autograph minutes of the first and second meetings of the association held on April 18 and 22, 1839; W. J. Linton, secretary.
  - Mailing wrapper, Adams Express from McClurg Co., undated (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 369)
  - Pages removed from serial publications, undated (Box 12, Folder 315-319)
    Miscellaneous groups of pages, their relationship to Linton is unknown.
  - Other papers, 1866–1902 (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 370)
- Other Papers, 1797–1922; Series VI; 2.08; 2 boxes
  The series holds a diverse collection of material related to W. J. Linton, his family members, and his colleagues. Important here is a set of graphite drawings of zoo animals by Walter Crane, made while he was serving an apprenticeship with Linton. Also present are graphic works by other artists, including James Gillray, that arrived with the Linton papers.
  - Linton autographs and letter fragments, undated (Box 12, Folder 320)
  - Linton, Ellen Wade, "W. J. Linton calendars", 1915–1922 (Box 12, Folder 321-322)
    Manuscript monthly calendars featuring quotes from Linton's writings, issued as Christmas tokens for family members.
    Another set of calendars (with variant verses) is in the Grace Linton Cook Papers about W. J. Linton (GEN MSS 1406).
  - Linton, William Wade
    - "A Birthday Present for Ducky", 1852 May 16 (Box 13, Folder 323)
      Handmade booklet for Emily Wade Linton, with watercolor drawings; laid in: sketches of feathers and sea shells.
    - "Geography", undated (Box 13, Folder 324)
      Autograph manuscript booklet with four chapters on the world geography.
  - Mansfield, Howard, notebook, 1911 July (Box 13, Folder 325)
    With autograph notes on his trip to England and notes of about Linton
    Gift of Margaret Linton Mather, 1929.
  - Mazzini, Joseph, "Mazzini: Letters on Italy. 1839", undated (Box 13, Folder 326)
    Bound volume of Mazzini's "Letters" I-IV cut from serials, with pencil markings.
  - Notes on Linton family, undated (Box 13, Folder 327)
    Manuscript notes in unidentified hands.
  - Artwork by others
    - Crane, Walter, fourteen drawings of animals; graphite on card, undated (Box 13, Folder 328)
      Sketched in the Zoological Gardens, Regents Park, London, between 1858 and 1862, while Crane was apprenticed to Linton.
    - Gifford, R. Swain, untitled landscape; etching, 1868 (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 371)
      Inscribed by the artist: "W. J. Linton Esqr with the regards of R. Swain Gifford NY 1868."
    - Gillray, James, "Bank-notes, paper-money, French-alarmists, O, the devil, the devil! ah! poor John-Bull!!!"; etching, hand colored, 1797 March (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 372)
    - Sibson, Thomas, "Oh Man Man, how often do you carry with you that which you say pursues you"; iron gall ink on paper, undated (Box 13, Folder 329)
    - Unidentified artist, three copies of a printed reproduction of an oil painting mounted on linen, undated (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 373)
    - Other reproductions, undated (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 374-375)